Dive into quick sort algorithm and its complexity.
Quickstart is a sorting algorithm based on the divide and conquer approach, where an array is divided
into submarines by selecting a pivot element element selected from there.
So while dividing the array, the first step or the second step, the pivot element should be positioned
in such a way that elements less than pivot are kept on the left side, and elements greater than the
pivot are kept on the right side of the pivot.
The left and right boroughs are also divided using the same approach.
The elements less than a pivot are kept to the left left side of their pivot, and the elements greater
than the pivot are kept on the right side of the.
This process continues until each submarine contains a single element at the point where containing
an element, only one single element elements are already sorted.
Finally, elements are combined to form a sorted array, so that quick search algorithm here is an example.
We have.
Here in this area, we took a pivot.
We make the pivot that that is greater than we start from here.
So we're selecting that pivot and the higher higher than the pivot is kept on the right and the low
would be making a pivot to the left.
So they are kept to the left for this.
We have made that 32 as a pivot.
The higher elements are on the right and the lower are on the left and we start dividing.
We divide it into a quick sort on the left side.
Divide it into two suburbs, the first one and the second one, and we applied the same algorithm,
the same concept by choosing a pivot here like 18.
The.
Elements of greater than 18 are kept on the right, while the elements having less value less than that
of what is kept on the left after reaching this and making this separate is fully fully following.
The concept of the left is less than the pivot and the right is greater than the pivot.
Then it is segmented into elements on into single elements, and here is the same.
So on the right side is followed the same.
We choose a pivot here 30 61 and 50 50 is a pivot.
High to the right and left, no elements, we divide it into two elements.
After reaching this step like this, the first element, the second element, the third, fourth and
fifth after reaching this.
Step by using a single elements or reaching the single elements.
We just combine them into one final sorted array, so we just put in nine here.
We put 18 after it, 23 after it, 50 after and 60 after to for this editing.
OK, so this is that quick sort algorithm, a quick thought algorithm start by taking an array and the
left.
This is the algorithm that we are going to implement it into in the next videos, in sea language and
in Java.
So.
We took an array that we are going to start with, but the left most index and the rightmost index.
OK, then we check if the left most index less than the rightmost index, then the pivot index part
the chart we call the method partition that we are going to create.
So we passed the array and the left most index and the right and most index we are segmenting here and
part the chin.
This is the partition like this and part of this?
OK.
And we call recursively that quick sword method again and gain by blessing.
And today we pass left most index and the pivot index minus then the quick sort.
Also being cold because the recursively is being applied and the pivot index is passed as a barometer
of the left most index and the rightmost index is what's also called and and passed as the parameter.
Remember, guys, there is one trick here we have called two times a recursively that quick sort.
But the first time is the left most index.
We passed this parameter and in the second step we passed the rightmost index as a sixth as the and
as a parameter for that right.
So this will allow us to make this recursively to sort fully supporting the left at the first after
we have reaches that segmentation and we have partitioned it into single elements.
We go back and we call a recursively the quick sort method and we pass that right.
Most index and we start partition the right.
SEC.
OK, so.
This is the algorithm that we are going to to implement and the next videos.
Let's talk about the partition method partition method took into IRA.
As and left most index and right index indexes, arguments and parameters, so set right, most indexes
pivot index.
This is the first step and store the index equal to the left most index minus one store it into their
store index.
And make a loop for all the elements from it to the left, not left most index to the right most index,
so we are going best through all the elements and the tried to swap them.
If the element at index I less than pivot, then swap the elements and store them to the left, otherwise
put them to the right.
This is the part, the method that follows and here and all that quick sort algorithm.
OK.
Let's talk about the complexity, the time complexity for the quick sort algorithm is in the best case
is end times luck and because we are making the best case occurs when the partition process always picked
the middle element as before.
So the best case is here, it's occurring while taking, always picking the middle element.
As before, the worst case scenario occurs when the partition process always pick the greatest or the
smallest element as if so on the square.
The average is end times.
Look at OK to do average case analysis.
We need to consider all possible permutation of array and calculate time taken by every permutation,
which does not look easy.
So this is like an average closer for the best.
The space complexity, the space complexity of of the quick sort is plug and OK and their stability,
it is not stable.
So is a quick stress or stable.
The default implementation is not stable.
However, any sorting algorithm can be made stable by considering the this that in this is as comparison,
but a meter.
Okay, this is the trick.
This is the trick by considering that in this is as comparison per meter.
This is the trick that makes that any sorting algorithm considered as a stable.
So after learning much more about the quick sort, let's implement it in C language and next videos
that we are going to solve the exercise.